John E. Pease Papers VHP2005/6
CCSU Veterans History Project
John E. Pease Papers
Bulk, 1943-1945
1940 - 1945, 1998, 2008
VHP2005/6
CCSU Veterans History Project
258.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
The collection details John E. Pease experience in World War II. He enlisted in the Marines in 1943 he became a member of the Special Weapons Division in which he served in the Pacific Campaign until his discharge in 1946. The collection consists of personal and military manuscripts, news articles, and photographs. The records provide evidence of the massive loss of American life during the battle for Tarawa, and air attacks by the Japanese on American bases.
Pease, John E., (John Edward), 1923 -
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Arrangement note
Series I: Presonal Papers
Series II: Military Documents
Series III: Publications
Series IV: Multi-Media
Biographical/Historical note
John Pease enlisted in the U.S. Marine Corps in December of 1943. He left for basic training on Parris Island on January 19, 1944. After completion of basic training, Pease was sent to Camp Lejeune (NC) for additional training and unit assignment. His unit shipped to American Samoa on a former luxury liner. On American Samoa, he learned how to use the 30 caliber Browning machine gun, and he and a squad of eight others kept guard on the island. After five months on American Samoa, his unit was shipped to Wellington, New Zealand to pick up additional troops. Pease's unit spent 57 days aboard the ship awaiting the troop's arrival. From there they sailed to the Tarawa Atoll, where the "Battle of Tarawa" had just begun. Pease describes the battle in detail, and what the typical marine survived during the battle with the Japanese. From Tarawa he was sent to a naval hospital in Hawaii because he contracted Filariasis, a disease that is passed to humans from mosquitoes. Due to this disease Pease was not sent back to the Pacific theater after his hospitalization. Instead he was sent to a naval shipyard in Birmington, WA, where he worked as a guard for the rest of his service time. He was discharged in February of 1946 and returned home to Connecticut. He worked for a time at Hamilton Standard Propeller and attended college at night. He then began work for the Resolute Insurance Company in Hartford, CT, where he stayed for 35 years, eventually becoming the Vice-President of the Life insurance division. Pease joined the American Legion and the VFW. At the end of the interview Pease shows a collection of items that he brought back from the war.
United States. Marine Corps. Marines, 2nd. Battalion, 2nd .; United States. Marine Corps.; American Samoa; Camp Lejeune (N.C.); Hawaii; Interviews; Manuscript; New Zealand; Parris Island (S.C.); Photographs; Tarawa Atoll (Kiribati); Tarawa, Battle of, Kiribati, 1943; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Area; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2005/6.I
  - John Pease's medals, 2005; VHP2005/6.I.1
  - a white Japanese handkerchief, cira 1940s; VHP2005/6.I.2
  - a 10 dollar shilling from New Zealand, cira 1940s; VHP2005/6.I.3
  - a 1938 Japanese 50 Sen banknote, VHP2005/6.I.4
  - Interview Synopsis, April 29, 2005; VHP2005/6.I.5
- Series II: Military Documents, VHP2005/6.II
  - Basic Field Manual Bayonet, M1905, Jan. 2, 1940; VHP2005/6.II.01; 21.0 Digital objects
  - Combination Score Book for U.S. Rifles M1903 and M1, and the Browning automatic rifle M1918A2, March 29, 1942; VHP2005/6.II.02; 6.0 Digital objects
  - "Going back to cilivians life" Pamphlet, Aug. 20, 1945; VHP2005/6.II.03; 48.0 Digital objects
  - The Marine's Handbook, 1940; VHP2005/6.II.04; 130.0 Digital objects
  - John Pease’s examination answer sheet, circa 1940s; VHP2005/6.II.05; 3.0 Digital objects
  - List of accessories for an M.G. M1917A1 (Browning machine gun), circa 1940s; VHP2005/6.II.06; 3.0 Digital objects
- Series III: Publications, VHP2005/6.III
  - Hamilton Standard Newsletter Vol. 3 No. 1, July 6, 1944; VHP2005/6.III.1
  - Leatherneck Magazine, November 2003; VHP2005/6.III.2; 4.0 Digital objects
- Series IV: Multi-Media, VHP2005/6.IV
  - Subseries a: Still Images, VHP2005/6.IV
    - John Pease in dress blues, April 1943; VHP2005/6.IV.1
    - Basic training buddies, Parris Island, SC, 1943; VHP2005/6.IV.2
    - John Pease, Unknown Soldier, and George Neelans (l to r), Parris Island, SC, 1943; VHP2005/6.IV.3
    - Parris Island, SC. Persons(L to R): John Pease, unknown, George Neelans, 1943; VHP2005/6.IV.4
    - Soldier with last name "McCarthy", Parris Island, SC 1943, VHP2005/6.IV.5
    - Fitzgerald playing horseshoes; Bremerton, WA 1944, 1943; VHP2005/6.IV.6
    - John Pease and unknown soldier in front of sentry shack at the main gate. Bremerton ,WA, 1944; VHP2005/6.IV.7
    - John Pease and Unknown Soldier (l to r) at the Ammunition Depot main gate sentry shack, Bremerton, WA, 1944; VHP2005/6.IV.8
    - John Pease on horseback at Bremerton, WA 1945, VHP2005/6.IV.9
    - John Pease at Naval Ammunition Depot in Bremerton, WA 1945, VHP2005/6.IV.10
    - (L to R) Cpl. Rampick, unknown, John Pease at Bremerton, WA, 1945; VHP2005/6.IV.11
    - John Pease at home, June 3, 2005; VHP2005/6.IV.12
  - Subseries b: Moving Images, VHP2005/6.IVb
    - Oral history interview, April 29, 2005; VHP2005/6.IVb.1; 1.0 dvd; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2005/6, Box VHP Interview #1)